<resource xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://datacite.org/schema/kernel-4"
          xsi:schemaLocation="http://datacite.org/schema/kernel-4 https://schema.datacite.org/meta/kernel-4.4/metadata.xsd">
  <identifier identifierType="DOI">10.58137/001-2023-52</identifier>
  <creators>
    <creator>
      <creatorName nameType="Personal">Falkenstein, Ludwig</creatorName>
      <givenName>Ludwig</givenName>
      <familyName>Falkenstein</familyName>
      <nameIdentifier nameIdentifierScheme="GND" schemeURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">120353709</nameIdentifier>
      <affiliation xml:lang="de">Rheinisch-Westfälische Technische Hochschule Aachen</affiliation>
    </creator>
  </creators>
  <titles>
    <title xml:lang="de">Gallia Pontificia online: Ludwig Falkenstein, Reims I: Erzbischöfe, bearbeitet von Robert
      Friedrich und Sebastian Gensicke, herausgegeben von Rolf Große, Paris 2023, Nr. <nrReplace />
    </title>
    <title xml:lang="de" titleType="AlternativeTitle">GPO Reims I: Erzbischöfe, Nr. <nrReplace /></title>
  </titles>
  <publisher>Deutsches Historisches Institut Paris</publisher>
  <publicationYear>2023</publicationYear>
  <resourceType resourceTypeGeneral="Dataset">Dataset</resourceType>
  <subjects>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/" subjectScheme="GND"
             valueURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/4044562-8">Papsturkunde
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/" subjectScheme="GND"
             valueURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/4049007-5">Regest
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/" subjectScheme="Wikidata"
             valueURI="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1933248">Regest
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/" subjectScheme="GND"
             valueURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/4062135-2">Diplomatik
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/" subjectScheme="Wikidata"
             valueURI="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q378426">Diplomatik
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/" subjectScheme="GND"
             valueURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/4044561-6">Papst
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/" subjectScheme="Wikidata"
             valueURI="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q12829728">Papsttum
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/" subjectScheme="GND"
             valueURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/7503821-3">Frühmittelalter
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/" subjectScheme="Wikidata"
             valueURI="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q202763">Frühmittelalter
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/" subjectScheme="GND"
             valueURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/7503822-5">Hochmittelalter
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/" subjectScheme="Wikidata"
             valueURI="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q212685">Hochmittelalter
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/" subjectScheme="Wikidata"
             valueURI="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1559826">Göttinger Papsturkundenwerk
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/" subjectScheme="GND"
             valueURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118721461">Paul Fridolin Kehr
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/" subjectScheme="Wikidata"
             valueURI="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q108748">Paul Fridolin Kehr
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/" subjectScheme="GND"
             valueURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118551280">Erzbischof Hinkmar von Reims
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/" subjectScheme="Wikidata"
             valueURI="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q712257">Hinkmar von Reims
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/" subjectScheme="GND"
             valueURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/104353503">Henricus, Remensis
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/" subjectScheme="Wikidata"
             valueURI="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q966305">Heinrich von Frankreich, Erzbischof von Reims
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/" subjectScheme="GND"
             valueURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/118819712">Alexander III., Papst
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/" subjectScheme="Wikidata"
             valueURI="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q160116">Alexander III., Papst
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="http://www.geonames.org/" subjectScheme="Geonames"
             valueURI="http://www.geonames.org/3017382">Frankreich
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="http://www.geonames.org/" subjectScheme="Geonames"
             valueURI="http://www.geonames.org/3027258">Champagne
    </subject>
    <subject xml:lang="de" schemeURI="http://www.geonames.org/" subjectScheme="Geonames"
             valueURI="http://www.geonames.org/2984114">Reims
    </subject>
  </subjects>
  <contributors>
    <contributor contributorType="Researcher">
      <contributorName nameType="Personal">Friedrich, Robert</contributorName>
      <givenName>Robert</givenName>
      <familyName>Friedrich</familyName>
      <nameIdentifier nameIdentifierScheme="ORCID" schemeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0003-0230-8917</nameIdentifier>
      <affiliation xml:lang="de">Universität Greifswald</affiliation>
    </contributor>
    <contributor contributorType="Researcher">
      <contributorName nameType="Personal">Gensicke, Sebastian</contributorName>
      <givenName>Sebastian</givenName>
      <familyName>Gensicke</familyName>
      <nameIdentifier nameIdentifierScheme="ORCID" schemeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0002-7479-307X</nameIdentifier>
      <affiliation xml:lang="de">Deutsches Historisches Institut Paris</affiliation>
    </contributor>
    <contributor contributorType="Editor">
      <contributorName nameType="Personal">Große, Rolf</contributorName>
      <givenName>Rolf</givenName>
      <familyName>Große</familyName>
      <nameIdentifier nameIdentifierScheme="GND" schemeURI="http://d-nb.info/gnd/">130539767</nameIdentifier>
      <nameIdentifier nameIdentifierScheme="ORCID" schemeURI="https://orcid.org/">0000-0001-7651-7362</nameIdentifier>
      <affiliation xml:lang="de">Deutsches Historisches Institut Paris</affiliation>
    </contributor>
    <contributor contributorType="HostingInstitution">
      <contributorName>Max Weber Stiftung – Deutsche Geisteswissenschaftliche Institute im Ausland</contributorName>
      <nameIdentifier nameIdentifierScheme="ROR" schemeURI="https://ror.org/">02esxtn62</nameIdentifier>
    </contributor>
  </contributors>
  <descriptions>
    <description xml:lang="fr" descriptionType="Abstract">Les regestes pontificaux concernant les archevêques de Reims,
      1&#160;162 numéros au total, constituent le premier corpus de sources rendu accessible aux chercheurs dans le
      cadre de la »Gallia Pontificia online« (GPO). C’est donc la première fois que l’on dispose d’une documentation
      complète sur les relations qu’a entretenu le plus important des archevêques français avec la curie durant le haut
      Moyen Âge et le Moyen Âge central.
      Le matériel provient du fonds de Ludwig Falkenstein, décédé le 29 novembre 2015. Ce médiéviste d’Aix-la-Chapelle
      fut sans aucun doute l’un des plus grands spécialistes de l’histoire de Reims au Moyen Âge. Jean-Loup Lemaitre lui
      a consacré une nécrologie très fournie (Francia 43 [2016], S. 469–473). Sa veuve, Ruth Falkenstein, a cédé le
      droit d’exploiter et de publier son legs scientifique à Rolf Große.
      Ludwig Falkenstein a commencé ses recherches sur les actes pontificaux de Reims dès 1965 et s’y est consacré
      jusqu’à la veille de sa mort. Malheureusement, il ne lui fut pas donné de les achever définitivement pour la
      publication. C’est pourquoi il était nécessaire de les relire en profondeur et de les remanier pour la publication
      numérique.
      Robert Friedrich et Sebastian Gensicke ont joué un rôle décisif dans ce processus. En poste à l’IHA en tant que
      doctorants, ils ont, sous la direction de Rolf Große, non seulement adapté les regestes sur le plan rédactionnel,
      mais ils les ont aussi balisés en langage XML selon le schéma CEI/TEI, en plus d’avoir ajouté une trentaine de
      numéros. La bibliographie a été complétée par de nouvelles références, sans que cela soit exhaustif. De plus, des
      liens vers les éditions, les regestes, la littérature secondaire et les manuscrits numérisés ont été ajoutés.
      Ils ont été aidés par des stagiaires de l’IHA, notamment par Sarah Anabel Lang, ainsi que par Thomas Billard,
      Isabel Dillenberger, Ronja Fischer, Leonhard Fleischer, Paul Förder, Hilda Hetz, Michaela Kästl, Thomas Lebrun,
      Colombe le Roy, Maria Weidel et Simon Wellner.
    </description>
    <description xml:lang="de" descriptionType="Abstract">Die Papstregesten der Erzbischöfe von Reims, insgesamt 1&#160;162
      Nummern, sind das erste Quellencorpus, das im Rahmen der »Gallia Pontificia online« (GPO) der Forschung zugänglich
      gemacht wird. Somit liegt erstmals die umfassende Dokumentation der Kurialbeziehungen des wichtigsten
      französischen Erzbischofs im frühen und hohen Mittelalter vor.
      Das Material stammt aus dem Nachlass des am 29. November 2015 verstorbenen Aachener Mediävisten Ludwig
      Falkenstein, eines der besten Kenner der Reimser Geschichte im Mittelalter. Jean-Loup Lemaitre hat ihm einen
      ausführlichen Nachruf gewidmet (Francia 43 [2016], S. 469–473). Das Recht, seinen wissenschaftlichen Nachlass
      auszuwerten und zu veröffentlichen, übertrug die Witwe, Ruth Falkenstein, an Rolf Große.
      Ludwig Falkenstein begann seine Arbeit an den Reimser Papsturkunden bereits 1965 und widmete sich ihnen bis kurz
      vor seinem Tod. Leider blieb es ihm nicht vergönnt, die Arbeit für die Veröffentlichung endgültig abzuschließen.
      Deshalb war es nötig, die Texte einer erneuten Durchsicht zu unterziehen und für die digitale Publikation
      aufzubereiten.
      An diesem Vorgang tragen Robert Friedrich und Sebastian Gensicke entscheidenden Anteil. Als Doktoranden am DHIP
      beschäftigt, haben sie die Regesten, unter Leitung von Rolf Große, nicht nur redaktionell bearbeitet, sondern auch
      um ca. 30 Nummern ergänzt und nach dem CEI/TEI-Schema in XML ausgezeichnet. Neuere Editionen, Regestenwerke und
      Literatur wurden nachgetragen; dabei konnte allerdings keine Vollständigkeit erreicht werden. Zudem wurden Links
      zu Digitalisaten von Literatur und Handschriften eingefügt.
      Unterstützt wurden sie von Praktikantinnen und Praktikanten am DHIP, vor allem von Sarah Anabel Lang, ferner von
      Thomas Billard, Isabel Dillenberger, Ronja Fischer, Leonhard Fleischer, Paul Förder, Hilda Hetz, Michaela Kästl,
      Thomas Lebrun, Colombe le Roy, Maria Weidel und Simon Wellner.
    </description>
    <description xml:lang="en" descriptionType="Abstract">The regesta of the Archbishops of Reims, a total of 1.162
      numbers, are the first source corpus to be made available to researchers within the framework of »Gallia
      Pontificia online« (GPO). Thus, for the first time, the comprehensive documentation of the curial relations of the
      most important French archbishop in the early and high Middle Ages is made available.
      The material comes from the estate of the Aachen medievalist Ludwig Falkenstein, who was one of the best experts
      on the history of Reims in the Middle Ages. He died on 29 November 2015. Jean-Loup Lemaitre dedicated an extensive
      obituary to him (Francia 43 [2016], p. 469–473). The right to evaluate and publish his scholarly estate was
      transferred by his widow, Ruth Falkenstein, to Rolf Große.
      Ludwig Falkenstein began his work on the Reims papal documents as early as 1965 and devoted himself to them until
      shortly before his death. Unfortunately, he was not able to finally complete the work for publication. It was
      therefore necessary to review the texts again and prepare them for digital publication.
      Robert Friedrich and Sebastian Gensicke played a decisive role in this process. As doctoral students at the GHIP,
      they not only edited the registers under the supervision of Rolf Große, but also added about 30 numbers and marked
      them up in XML according to the CEI/TEI scheme. Newer editions, editions of regesta and literature were added. It
      was, however, not possible to achieve completeness. In addition, links to digital copies of literature and
      manuscripts were inserted.
      They were supported by interns at the GHIP, especially Sarah Anabel Lang, as well as Thomas Billard, Isabel
      Dillenberger, Ronja Fischer, Leonhard Fleischer, Paul Förder, Hilda Hetz, Michaela Kästl, Thomas Lebrun, Colombe
      le Roy, Maria Weidel and Simon Wellner.
    </description>
  </descriptions>
  <geoLocations>
    <geoLocation>
      <geoLocationPlace>Reims</geoLocationPlace>
      <geoLocationPoint>
        <pointLatitude>49.265278</pointLatitude>
        <pointLongitude>4.028611</pointLongitude>
      </geoLocationPoint>
    </geoLocation>
    <geoLocation>
      <geoLocationPlace>Champagne</geoLocationPlace>
      <geoLocationPoint>
        <pointLatitude>49.0000</pointLatitude>
        <pointLongitude>4.3000</pointLongitude>
      </geoLocationPoint>
    </geoLocation>
    <geoLocation>
      <geoLocationPlace>Frankreich</geoLocationPlace>
      <geoLocationPoint>
        <pointLatitude>46.0000</pointLatitude>
        <pointLongitude>2.0000</pointLongitude>
      </geoLocationPoint>
    </geoLocation>
  </geoLocations>
  <language>de</language>
  <relatedIdentifiers>
    <relatedIdentifier relatedIdentifierType="DOI" relationType="IsPartOf">10.58137/001-2023-0</relatedIdentifier>
  </relatedIdentifiers>
  <formats>
    <format>tei+xml</format>
  </formats>
  <rightsList>
    <rights rightsURI="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/legalcode">Creative Commons Attribution Share
      Alike 4.0 International
    </rights>
  </rightsList>
</resource>